Mahatma Gandhi emerged as the leader who could
channel this widespread anger into organized resistance.
In 1920, he launched the Non-Cooperation Movement, based
on his philosophy of Satyagraha or non-violent resistance.
Gandhi's strategy was revolutionary yet simple: if Indians
stopped cooperating with British institutions and withdrew their
support, the colonial system would collapse from within.
He believed that British rule in India survived
only because Indians participated in it - as
government employees, students in British schools, buyers of
British goods, and participants in British legal systems.
Gandhi called upon Indians to boycott British goods,
resign from government jobs, withdraw children from government
schools, and refuse to participate in British courts.