After World War I ended in 1918, India was seething with discontent.
The British had promised self-governance in return for India's
support during the war, but these promises remained unfulfilled.
The economic burden of the war had devastated
India's economy, leading to widespread poverty and unemployment.
Adding fuel to the fire were two major incidents: the
Rowlatt Act of 1919, which gave the British government sweeping
powers to arrest and detain Indians without trial,
and the horrific Jallianwala Bagh massacre in Amritsar, where
British troops fired on unarmed civilians, killing hundreds.
These events shattered Indian faith in British justice and created
the perfect conditions for a mass movement against colonial rule.