Although the Non-Cooperation Movement was called off, its impact
on Indian politics and society was profound and lasting.
For the first time, millions of ordinary Indians had participated
in a coordinated struggle against British rule, transforming the freedom
movement from an elite affair into a mass movement.
The movement established Gandhi as the undisputed leader of
Indian nationalism and demonstrated the power of non-violent resistance.
It also led to the emergence of new leaders and the
spread of nationalist ideas to villages and towns across India.
The economic boycott of British goods gave a
significant boost to Indian industries, particularly textiles.
Perhaps most importantly, the movement shattered the myth
of British invincibility and showed that colonial rule
could be challenged through organized, peaceful resistance.
The strategies and methods developed during this movement
would be refined and used in subsequent struggles,
ultimately leading to India's independence in 1947.