By 1922, the movement had gained tremendous
momentum, but it faced a critical test.
On February 5, 1922, in the small town of Chauri Chaura
in Uttar Pradesh, a group of protesters clashed with police.
When the police opened fire, the angry crowd retaliated by
setting fire to the police station, killing 22 policemen inside.
This incident of violence deeply troubled Gandhi, who believed
that the movement had lost its non-violent character.
Despite strong opposition from other leaders like Motilal Nehru and C.R. Das,
who argued that the movement was on the verge of success, Gandhi
made the controversial decision to call off the entire movement.
He believed that a movement based on violence, even if successful,
would not lead to the kind of free India he envisioned.