The Non-Cooperation Movement witnessed unprecedented participation
from all sections of Indian society.
Students left government schools and colleges in large numbers,
leading to the establishment of national schools and colleges.
Lawyers like Motilal Nehru, C.R. Das, and others gave up
their lucrative practices and refused to appear in British courts.
Government employees resigned from their posts, and
people began boycotting British goods, especially textiles.
The movement saw massive bonfires of foreign cloth,
and Indians embraced khadi or hand-spun cloth as
a symbol of self-reliance and resistance.
The movement also gained support from various communities -
Muslims joined due to the Khilafat issue, while peasants
and workers participated to protest against economic exploitation.
The Indian National Congress, under Gandhi's leadership, became
a mass organization for the first time.